a few months ago I presented a webinar
on
osteoporosis all the videos will
eventually be up on nutritionfacts.org
but I want to share the full recording
with you now stay tuned for the end for
lots of great Q&A um enjoy everyone and
welcome I'm Dr Michael Gregor coming to
you live from my treadmill for our very
first CME approved webinar CME
continuing medical education for doctors
and other Health Care Professionals as
such I'm proud to declare that I have no
relevant Financial relationships with
ineligible companies to
disclose that kind of Declaration
statement is necessary given a long
checkered past of big Pharma and medical
instrument company SE secretly propping
up paid shills to push their products so
now they just non secretly prop up paid
shills to push their products but at
least a little hard for them to hide but
before I cover the pros and cons of
drugs used to treat
osteoporosis let me start us off today
covering drugs that may cause
ITC fractures for 50-year-old white let
me start that at the beginning one in
five adults in the world may have
osteoporosis that's hundreds of millions
of people the word osteoporosis
literally means porous bone now most of
our bone is actually porous to begin
with this is what normal bone looks like
inside but this is
osteoporosis bone mineral density is
considered to be the standard measure
for the diagnosis of osteoporosis
although the bone mineral density cut
off for an osteoporosis diagnosis is
kind of arbitrary using the standard
definition osteoporosis may affect about
one in 10 women by age 60 2 and 10 by
age 74 and 10 by age 80 and six or seven
out of 10 by 90 osteoprosis is typically
thought of as a disease in women but
onethird of hip fractures occur in men
the lifetime risk for osteoporotic
fractures for 50-year-old white women
and men are 40% and 133%
respectively the good news is that
osteoporosis need not occur based on a
study of the largest twin registry in
the world less than 30% of osteoporotic
fracture risk is heritable leading the
researchers to conclude prevention of
fractures even in the oldest elderly
should focus on lifestyle
interventions this is consistent with
the enormous variation of hip fracture
rates around the world with the incident
of hip fracture varying tenfold or even
aund hundredfold between countries
suggesting that excessive bone loss is
not just an inevitable consequence of
Aging the United States preventive
Services Task Force an independent
scientific panel that sets
evidence-based clinical prevention
guidelines recommends osteoporosis
screening such as dexa bone mineral
density scan for all women age 65 and
older and potentially starting even
earlier than 65 for women at increased
risk such as having a parental history
of fracture being a smoker or an
excessive alcohol consumer or having low
body weight what should you do if you're
diagnosed or more importantly what
should you do to never be diagnosed
before exploring the drugs on offering
to treat osteoporosis there are some
drugs that may cause it so let's start
there stomach acid blocking proton pump
inhibitor drugs so-called ppis with
brand names like pisc pricd Nexium
protonics and aif effects are among the
most popular drugs in the world raking
in billions of dollars a year but then
in 2006 two observational studies out of
Europe suggested an association between
intake of this class of drugs and
increased risk of hip fracture and by
2010 the growing evidence forced the US
Food and Drug Administration to issue a
safety alert implicating PPI use with
fractures of the hip wrist and spine by
now there's been dozens of studies
involving more than two million people
that overall show higher hip fracture
rates among both long and short-term
users at all dose levels the irony is
that most people taking these drugs
shouldn't even be on them in the first
place these pprs are only FDA approved
for 10 days of use for the treatment of
hpylori up to two weeks for heartburn up
to eight weeks for acid reflux disease
and for 2 to six months for ulcers yet
in a community survey most users
remained on these drugs for more than a
year and more than 60% of patients were
taking them for inappropriate reasons
often wrongly prescribed for quotequote
indigestion for instance calls to stop
this massive overuse from regulatory
authorities have fallen on deaf doctor
ears and now that they're available over
the counter the problem of overuse have
just gotten even worse uh they can be
hard to stop taking since many patients
experience withdrawal symptoms that can
last for
weeks in fact if you take normal healthy
volunteers without any symptoms and put
them on these drugs for two months and
then covertly switch them to a placebo
without their knowledge all of the
sudden they can develop acid related
symptoms such as heartburn or acid
regurgitation so ending up worse off
than they were before they even started
taking the drugs in addition to bone
fractures this class of drugs has also
been linked to increased risk of other
possible long-term adverse effects
such as
pneumonia intestinal
infections kidney
failure stomach
cancer and cardiovascular disease in
fact the blood vessel effects could
explain the case report abrupt onset
profound erectile dysfunction in a
healthy young man after initiating
overthe counter
pilac oh and also premature
death there are IND indviduals with
conditions like Zer Alison syndrome
stricken with tumors that can cause
excess stomach acid secretion For Whom
the risk versus benefit of long-term use
may be acceptable but that's a far cry
from the hundred million ppis prescribed
annually in the United States
alone to deal with acid reflux without
drugs recommendations include weight
loss smoking sensation avoiding fatty
meals especially within 2 to 3 hours of
bedtime increased fi F consumption and
overall a more plant-based diet because
non vegetarianism is associated with
twice the odds of acid reflux induced
inflammation other classes of drugs have
been associated with hip fracture risk
include anti-depressants anti- Parkinson
drugs anticho anti-anxiety drugs oral
corticosteroids and the other major
class of heartburn drugs the H2 blockers
such as pepid Zantac Tagamet and
axid
okay so excessive bone loss is not just
an inevitable consequence of aging and
one of the things we can do to lower our
risk and that of our patients is to take
into account the potential skeletal side
effects of the drugs we take and
prescribe okay what about the drugs
prescribed to treat osteoporosis first
let me address efficacy
drug therapy for osteoporosis is
recommended for those 50 and older with
a history of past hippers spine
fractures those with hippers spine t-
scores of negative 2.5 or less and
postmenopausal women or men 50 and older
who don't make that cut off but have an
estimated 20% or higher risk of major
osteop prodoct fracture over the
subsequent decade or an estimated 3% or
greater risk of hip fracture
specifically a tcore is a measure of how
dense your bones are compared to a
30-year-old white woman since that's the
standard we tend to lose bone as we age
you can be labeled as having
osteoporosis even if you have completely
normal bone density for your age of
course just because your bone density
may be normal doesn't mean it's
necessarily optimal which is why the
national osteoporosis Foundation set out
these guidelines for drug
treatment though another reason perhaps
is because it gets substantial funding
from the drug industry which RS in
literally billions of dollars in profits
from osteoporosis drugs what does the
science say the primary drug class used
to treat osteoporosis is the bis
phosphinate sold as such Brands as
Fosamax actonel Boniva and reclass
they're most effective at reducing
vertebral fractures cutting the risk in
postmenopausal women from 2.8% down to
1.4% that's a relative risk reduction
50% but an absolute risk reduction of
only 1.4% meaning you'd have to treat 71
women to prevent just one woman from
getting a vertebral fracture
unfortunately the diagnosis of vertebral
fracture it's kind of wishy-washy
depending on how you define the changes
on x-ray the prevalence of vertial
fractures can vary as much as 3% to 90%
in the same elderly population almost
none to almost all they're also poorly
predictive of back pain or disability
vertebral factures can can certainly
lead to back pain reduce physical
function but only about a third are
symptomatic at all the most harmful
fractures are hip fractures despite most
of the clinical trials for osteoporosis
treatment being funded by the drug
companies themselves no primary
prevention benefit from this
phosphinates has been found for hip
fractures in other words taking these
drugs has not been convincingly shown to
prevent fracturing your hip in the first
place however having a prior fracture
doubles your risk of breaking another
bone so for those at high risk bis
phosphinate drugs May decrease the odds
of hip fracture by 25% though the
absolute risk reduction is again only
about 1% it may take treating 91 people
for three years to prevent one hip
fracture and overconfidence in the power
of pills and procedures for disease
prevention may be one of the reasons
doctors and patients alike May
undervalue diet and lifestyle approaches
in this study patients were asked to
estimate the number of fractures or
deaths prevented in a group of 5,000
patients undergoing each drug
intervention over a period of 10 years
the vast majority of people tended to
wildly overestimate the ability of
mammograms and colonoscopies to prevent
cancer deaths the power of drugs like
Fosamax to prevent hip fractures and
drugs like lipor to prevent fatal heart
attacks no wonder most people continue
to rely on drugs to save them but the
dirty little secret is that most people
said they wouldn't be willing to take
many of these drugs if they knew how
little benefit these products actually
offered and study of those undergoing
bone density scans the average 5-year
fracture risk that would motivate most
participants to consider preventive
medicine was 50 to 60% much higher than
their actual risk most patients want to
be told the truth they want to be told
what the chances are that the drugs will
actually benefit them but there's a
tension between the patient's right to
know and the likely reduction in their
willingness to take the drug if they
knew the truth in the bone density scan
survey participants greatly
overestimated made their own personal
risk for hip fracture thinking it was
around like 19% over the next 5 years
which is more than 10 times higher than
their actual risk of
1.4% rather than disabusing them of this
overestimate some suggest Physicians
should do the opposite Stoke fear in
patients who refuse to comply with
medication recommendations by increasing
their perceived susceptibility to
fragility fractures as well as their
perceived severity of suffering from a
fragility fracture since emotion can be
more motivating than re reason and
anecdotal evidence can be more effective
than evidence evidence a graphic
scenario of suffering and incapacitation
after hip fracture will enhance
emotional perception of this
threat but hip factures can indeed be
devastating and are associated with a
significant risk of ensuing death so
what about all the lives these drugs
must be saving well only about a quarter
of the deaths following fractures may be
attributable to the fracture itself so
most of the mortality risk may just be a
consequence of the comorbidities that is
the other diseases and poor health
status of people who tend to fracture
their hips so they might have died
anyway in that same time frame even if
they hadn't broken any bones this may
help explain why there are no saved
lives osteoporosis drug treatments
particularly B phosphinates fail to
significantly reduce overall
mortality okay so the efficacy of the
primary drug class used to treat
osteoporosis
is so slight on an individual basis that
most patients if truly fully informed
likely would not take them and that's
before even talking about the side
effects which I'll turn to right
now potential lack of efficacy is not
the only reason why most people
prescribe bosan drugs for osteoporosis
like fos Max tinel Boniva reclass may
stop taking them within a year there are
two rare but devastating side effects
oston necrosis of the jaw and atypical
femur fractures that contributed to
around a 50% drop in the use of this
class of drugs when they came to light
the New York Times article noting the
decline explained the reasoning reports
of the drugs causing jaw bones to rot
and thigh bones to snap in two have
shaken many osteoporosis so much that
they say they would rather take their
Chances with the disease the jaw rot
syndrome that prevents many from
initiating treatment for fear of their
jaw falling off can severely impact many
aspects of quality of life but is
exceedingly rare affecting at most one
in a thousand patients treated for
osteoporosis atypical femur fractures
can occur more frequently though as many
as one in 300 users treated for three
years they're called atypical because
they occur not after a fall or trauma
but just during Ro R activities like
walking twisting at the waist or even
just standing still your femur your
thigh bone the biggest bone in your body
just breaks in half too cruel an irony
from a drug that's supposed to protect
your bones this is what it looks like on
x-ray ouch bis phosphinates work by
inhibiting the action of a type of bone
cell called osteoclast your entire
skeleton is constantly being remodeled
with bone added in some spots and taken
away in others to conform to changing
demands the cells that are continually
laying down new bone are called oo blast
and the ones that chisel away old bone
are called OC class it makes sense then
that curbing the class could prevent
bone loss but by reducing the active
remodeling process B phosphinates can
freeze the skeleton allowing for the
accumulation of micro cracks over time
resulting in stress fractures other
osteoporosis Strokes like denosumab sold
as Prolia prevent the same formation of
osteoclast in the first place and have
been plagued by the same kinds of rare
but disturbing side effects as with
anything in life it all comes down to
risks versus benefits I mean how many
hip fractures are prevented for every
femur that snaps it depends on your race
and how long you're on these drugs after
5 years in white women 36 hip fractures
are prevented for every atypical femur
fracture Hispanic women only get half
the benefit about 18 to1 and for Asian
women it's only about five hip fractures
prevented for every femur fracture
caused the study claims it failed to
recw enough data on black women at 10
years of drug exposure the ratios get
worse 16 to1 for white women 5 to1 for
Hispanic women and only 1.5 to1 for
Asian women meaning that the devastating
fractures prevented and caused in Asian
women are nearly
comparable a nationwide survey of
Resident Physicians found that knowledge
regarding osteoporosis diagnosis and
treatment was poor with a particularly
striking lack of knowledge regarding the
two serious drug side effects the good
news is that after stopping the drugs
the risk of femur fracture rapidly drops
by 70% within a year leading to the
suggestion that a drug holiday be
considered after a few years in the drug
to help mediate the
risk how crazy is that atypical femur
fracture data right I just Cann I get
over the irony of it all okay so between
the lack of sufficient efficacy and
these rare but devastating side effects
what can we do personally and how can we
counsel our patients to protect their
skeletons well before I get to Lifestyle
approaches let me first cover
supplements calcium and Vitamin D
supplements
in 12 short years government panels have
gone from suggesting widespread calcium
supplementation may be necessary to
protect our bones to do not
supplement what
happened it all started with a 2008
study in New Zealand short-term studies
had shown that calcium supplementation
may drop blood pressures by about a
point though the effect appears
transient disappearing after a few
months but better than nothing and
excess calcium in the gut can cause fat
malabsorption by forming soap fat
reducing saturated fat absorption and
increasing feal saturated fat content
and indeed if you take a couple Tums
along with your half bucket of KFC up to
twice as much fat could end up in your
stool and with less saturated fat
absorbed into your system your
cholesterol might drop so the New
Zealand researchers were expecting to
lower heart attack rates by giving women
calcium supplements to their
surprise there appeared to be more heart
attacks in the calcium supplement
group was this just a fluke All Eyes
turned to the Women's Health Initiative
the largest and longest randomized
control trial of calcium supplementation
the name might sound familiar that's the
study that uncovered how dangerous
hormone replacement therapy was
would it do the same for calcium
supplements the Women's Health
Initiative reported no adverse effects
however the majority of participants
were already taking calcium supplements
before the study started so effectively
the study was just comparing higher
versus lower dose calcium
supplementation not calcium supplements
versus no calcium supplements but if you
go back and just see what happened to
the women who started out not taking
supplements and then were randomized to
the supplement group
those who started calcium supplements
suffered significantly more heart
attacks or Strokes thus high dose or low
dose any calcium supplementation seems
to increase cardiovascular disease
risk so researchers went back digging
through other trial data for heart
attack and stroke rates and women
randomized to calcium supplements with
or without vitamin D added and confirmed
the danger and most of the population
studies agreed users of calcium
supplements tended to have increased
rates of heart disease stroke and
death the supplement industry was not
happy accusing the researchers of
relying in part on self-reported data
like they just asked people if they had
a heart attack or not rather than
verifying it and indeed long-term
calcium supplementation causes all sorts
of gastrointestinal distress including
twice the risk of being hospitalized
with acute symptoms that may have been
confused with a heart attack
but no The increased risk was seen
consistently across the trials whether
the heart attacks were verified or
not okay but why do calcium supplements
increase heart attack risk but not
calcium you get in your diet perhaps
because when you take calcium pills you
get a spike of calcium in your
bloodstream that you don't get just
eating calcium rich foods within hours
of taking supplemental calcium the
calcium levels in the blood shoot up and
can stti stay up as long as 8 hours this
evidently produces what's called a
hypercoagulable state your blood clots
more easily which could increase the
risk of clots in the heart and brain and
indeed higher calcium blood levels are
tied to higher heart attack and stroke
rates so the mechanism may be calcium
supplements leading to unnaturally large
rapid and sustained calcium levels in
the blood which can have a variety of
potentially problematic
effects calcium supplements have been
widely embraced on the grounds that they
are a natural and therefore Safe Way of
preventing osteoporotic fractures but
it's now becoming clear that taking
calcium in one or two daily doses is not
natural and that it does not reproduce
the same metabolic effects as calcium in
food the way nature intended and
furthermore the evidence is also
becoming steadily stronger that calcium
supplementation may not be safe that's
why most organizations providing advice
regarding bone health now recommend that
individuals should obtain their calcium
requirement from diet in preference to
supplements but if we can't reach it
through diet alone would the benefits to
the bones outweigh the risks to the
heart we'll find out
next okay so um um we still need to get
enough calcium but it should be through
Foods the way nature intended not
through Tums let's now turn to calcium
from calcium supplement safety to
calcium supplement
efficacy there has been an assumption
for decades that as a natural ele
calcium supplements must intrinsically
be safe but calcium supplementation is
neither natural nor risk-free but the
same could be said for every medication
on the planet yet doctors continue to
write billions of prescriptions for
drugs every year because the hope at
least is that the benefits outweigh the
risks so what about the benefits of
calcium supplements yes heart attacks
and strokes can be devastating but so
can hip fractures the risk of dying
shoots up in the months following a hip
fracture by one in five women don't last
a year after hip fracture and it may be
even worse for men on average apparently
cutting one's lifespan short by four or
five years and unfortunately these
dismal statistics don't seem to be
getting much better so even if calcium
supplements caused a few heart attacks
and strokes if they prevented many more
hip fractures then it might result in a
favorable risk benefit ratio so how
effective are calcium supplements in Pre
venting hip fractures we've known that
milk intake doesn't appear to help but
maybe that's because any potential
benefit of the calcium in milk may be
overshadowed by the increased risk of
fracture and death associated with the
galactose sugar in milk but what about
just the calcium in a calcium supplement
alone calcium intake in general does not
seem to be related to hip fracture risk
at all and when people have been given
calcium supplements uh Not only was
there no reduction in hip fracture risk
in increased risk is possible the
randomized control trial suggests that
64% greater risk of hip fractures with
calcium supplementation compared to just
like getting a placebo sugar
pill where did they even get this idea
then that calcium supplements might help
our bones it was this influential study
in 1992 that found a combination of
vitamin D and calcium supplements could
reduce hip FAS your race
43% but this was done on
institutionalized women like in a
nursing home who were vitamin D
deficient they weren't getting
sufficient sun exposure and so if you're
vitamin D deficient and you take vitamin
D and calcium no surprise your bones get
better but for women living
independently out in the community the
latest official recommendations for Cal
calcium and vitamin D supplementation to
prevent osteoporosis is unambiguous do
not supplement why because in the
absence of compelling evidence for
benefit taking supplements is not worth
any risk no matter how small now this is
not to say these supplements don't play
a role in treating osteoporosis or that
Vitamin D supplements might not be good
for other things but if you're just
trying to prevent fractures women living
outside of Institutions should not take
them and perhaps even in institutions in
this study instead of giving nursing
home residents vitamin D and calcium
supplements they randomized them to
sunlight exposure and calcium
supplements and those that got the
calcium pills had significantly
increased mortality lived shorter lives
than the sunshine only group although
calcium supplements don't appear to
prevent hip fractures they may reduce
overall fracture Risk by like 10% so
here's how the risk benefit shakes out
if a th people took calcium supplements
for 5 years we would expect 14 excess
heart attacks meaning 14 people would
have a heart attack that they would not
have had if they had not starten started
the calcium supplements so they were
effectively going to the store and
buying something that gave them a heart
attack plus 10 Strokes that otherwise
would not have happened and 13 deaths
people would have been alive had they
not started the supplements but that's
all balanced against the 26 fractures
that would be prevented now it's no fun
falling down breaking a wrist or
something but I think most people would
look at that risk benefit analysis and
conclude that calcium supplements are
doing more harm than
good given these findings the use of
these supplements should be discouraged
and individuals advised to obtain
calcium from their diet instead calcium
supplements have been associated with
elevated risk of Mard infarction heart
attacks whereas dietary calcium intake
has not how much calcium should we shoot
for interestingly unlike most other
nutrients there's no International
consensus uh for example in the UK the
recommendation for adults is 700
milligram a day but across the pond in
the us it's up to 1,200 a day whenever I
see that kind of huge discrepancy
between government panels I immediately
think scientific uncertainty political
maneuverings or
both newer data based on calcium balance
studies in which researchers make
detailed measurements of the calcium
going in and out of people suggests that
the calcium requirements for men and
women is lower than previously estimated
they found calcium balance was highly
resistant to change across a broad range
of intakes meaning our body is not
stupid if we eat less calcium our body
absorbs more and excretes less and if we
eat more calcium we absorb less and
excrete more to stay in balance
therefore current evidence suggests that
dietary calcium intake is not something
most people need to worry about this may
explain why in most studies no
relationship was found between calcium
intake and bone loss anywhere in the
skeleton because the body just kind of
takes care of it don't push it too far
though I mean once you get down to just
a few hundred milligrams a day you may
significantly get more bone
loss though there may not be great
evidence wor the us recommendations the
UK may have the right idea shooting for
between 500 and 1,000 milligrams a day
from dietary sources unless you've had
gastric bypass surgery or something and
need to take supplements for most people
though calcium supplements cannot be
considered safe or effective for
preventing bone
fractures okay so calcium supplements
appear to do more harm than good what
about taking taking Vitamin D
supplements let's find
out we've known for over 400 years that
muscle weakness was a common presenting
symptom of vitamin D deficiency bones
aren't the only organs that respond to
vitamin D muscles do too but as we age
our muscles lose vitamin D receptors
perhaps helping to explain the loss in
muscle strength as we age and indeed
vitamin D status does appear to predict
the decline in physical performance as
we age with lower vitamin D levels
linked to poorer
performance but maybe the vitamin D
didn't lead to weakness maybe the
weakness led to low vitamin
D vitamin D is the sunshine vitamin and
so if you're too weak to run around
outside that could explain the
correlation with lower levels to see if
it's cause and effect you have to put it
to the
test there's been about a dozen
randomized control trials Vitamin D
supplements versus sugar pills put all
the studies together and older men and
women do get significant protection from
Falls with vitamin D especially among
those who start out with relatively low
levels leading the conservative uspstf
the US preventive Services Task Force
the official prevent guidelines setting
body and the American geriatric Society
to recommend vitamin D supplementation
for those at high risk for
Falls we're not quite sure the mechanism
though randomized controlled trials have
found that vitamin D boosts Global
muscle strength particularly in the
quads which are important for fall
prevention though Vitamin D supplements
have also been shown to improve
balance
so it may also be a neurological effect
or even a cognitive effect we've known
for about 20 years that older men and
women who stop walking when a
conversation starts are at particularly
high risk of falling over a six-month
time frame few of those who could walk
and talk at the same time would go on to
fall but 80% of those who stopped when a
conversation is initiated ended up
falling
other high-risk groups that should
supplement include those who've already
fallen once or are unsteady or on a
variety of heart brain and blood
pressure drugs that can increase fall
risk there's also a test called get up
and go which anyone can do at home you
time how long it takes you to get up
from an armchair walk 10 ft turn around
walk back and sit down if it takes you
longer than 10 seconds then you may be
at high
risk
so how much vitamin D should you take
seems to take at least 700 to 1,000
units a
day the American geriatric Society
recommends a total of 4,000 a day though
based on the rationale that this should
get about 90% of people up to the Target
vitamin D blood level of 75 nanomoles
per liter a th000 should do it for the
majority of people
51% but they recommend 4,000 to capture
92% of the
population then you don't have to
routinely test levels since you would
get most people up there and it's
considerably below the proposed upper
tolerable intake of 10,000 a
day they do not recommend periodic Mega
does because it's hard to get patients
to comply with pills why not just give
people one meados like 500,000 units
once once a year like when you come in
for a flu shot or something so every
year you can at least guarantee everyone
gets an annual spike in D levels that
last a few months it's unnatural but
certainly convenient for the doctor at
least the problem is that it actually
increases fall risk a 30% increase in
Falls in those first three months of the
spike similar results were found in
other meados trials
it may be a matter of too much of a good
thing see vitamin D May improve physical
performance reduce chronic pain and
improve mood so much that you start
moving around more and thereby increase
fall risk you give people a whopping
dose of D and you get a burst in
physical mental and social
functioning and it may take time for
your motor control to catch up with your
improved muscle function
it would be like giving someone a sports
car all of a sudden when they've been
used to driving some beater you got to
take it
slow it's possible though that such
unnaturally high doses may actually
damage the
muscles the evidence they site in
support is a meat industry study showing
you can improve the tenderness of staks
by feeding steers a few million units of
vitamin D so the concern is that such
high doses may be over tenderizing our
own muscles as well so yeah higher D
levels are associated with a progressive
drop in fracture risk but too much
vitamin D may be
harmful the bottom line is that vitamin
D supplementation appears to help but
the strongest and most consistent
evidence for prevention of serious Falls
is
exercise if you compare the two yes
taking vitamin D May lower your fall
risk compared to placebo
but strength and balance training with
or without vitamin D may be even more
powerful it's so interesting watching
those uh those old uh those old videos
sorry if I made anyone seasick with
those tilting tilting
PDFs um but it was it's kind of a neat
blast from the past there all right
anyway um so periodic annual or even
monthly Mega doses of Vitamin D may
increase risk what's the best daily
dosing well let me share a study with
you that came out after I finished that
video um which I think is really
enlightening I wish it was around when
the video was made so I could include it
okay so I'm what I'm going to do is I'm
going to share this PDF here and let's
see how this
works okay hopefully before you you
should see a
PDF um all right uh I'm gonna uh zoom in
a little bit here to this blue quote
hopefully you can read it um okay so
what we're looking at here this is a
year-long randomized double blind paal
control trial of seven different daily
doses of vitamin D for elderly women who
started out low in
D okay um and what they
found sorry I'm on a scroll quick
speaking of making people
sick um and uh so looking at the green
quote here you can see that which found
that the low doses appeared to be
useless um 400 or 800 international
units a day but there was a significant
reduction in Fall rates among those
taking the medium doses 1,600 2400 or
3,200 units a day and significantly
higher fall rate for taking 4,000 a day
or 10,000 a day compared to the medium
doses so you'll remember back in that in
the video um I talked about um some
authori suggesting 4,000 after this
study um I would suggest that's too much
um unless you have some reason to think
otherwise all right I'm going to switch
over uh uh to another study here um this
is a threeyear study
ready um you can close your eyes till I
finish I'm looking for a a green quote
is no green quote in here all right well
let me maybe it's the blue quote and
then I messed that up all right I'm
gonna zoom in here whoa what just
happened I just started to printing it
all right zoom
in um um okay three-year study found
higher doses 4,000 or 10,000 a day may
also lower bone mineral density oh look
can I like make it check it out lower
bone mental density can I make pretty
colors I don't know
anyway uh I'm getting too PDF happy um
but uh so uh so that may help explain um
uh the uh increased um fracture risk
okay moving on uh to the next PDF okay
um what's
the adverse
effects didn't we just talk about
[Music]
um may also lower bone mineral
density oh oh and I I was just uh it
turns out that action may be worse um
for women than in men I guess that was
the only point I was making this all
right let's go back to the videos here
um uh when I say it's better to get
calcium from Foods most people
immediately think Dair right but two
videos ago in this webinar um you know I
talked I very
briefly um you know mentioned and kind
of flashed by remember you're gonna get
all these videos so you can watch it
slow and pause and you know I know this
everything flies by quick I'm just
obviously trying to pack a huge amount
of information into uh into every second
here um but uh you know I talked about
how milk intake doesn't appear to help
um but maybe because any potential
benefit of calcium may be overshadowed
by the increased risk of fracture and
death associated with the galactose
sugar and milk you say wait a second
increased risk of fracture and death let
us definitely address that
next milk is touted to build strong
bones but a compilation of all the best
studies found no association between
milk consum consumption and hip fracture
risk so drinking milk as an adult may
not help bones but what about in
adolescence Harvard researchers decided
to put it to the test Studies have shown
that greater milk consumption during
childhood and Adolescence contributes to
Peak bone masses therefore expected to
help avoid osteoporosis and bone
fractures in later life but that's not
what they found milk consumption during
teenage years was not associated with a
lower risk of hip fracture and if
anything milk consumption was associated
with a an increase in fracture risk in
men it appears that the extra boost in
total body bone mineral density you get
from getting extra calcium is lost
within a few years even if you keep the
calcium supplementation up this suggests
a partial explanation for the
long-standing Enigma that hip fracture
rates are highest in populations with
the greatest milk
consumption maybe an explanation why
they're not lower but why would they be
higher this Enigma irked a Swedish
research team puzzled because studies
again and again had shown a tendency of
higher risk of fracture with a higher
intake of milk well there is a rare
birth Effect called galactosemia where
babies are born without the enzymes
needed to detoxify the galactose found
in milk so they end up with elevated
levels of galactose in their blood which
can cause bone loss even as kids so
maybe the Swedish researchers figured
even in normal people that can detoxify
the stuff it might not be good for the
bones to be drinking it every day and
galactose doesn't just hurt the bones
that's what scientists use to cause
premature aging in lab animals they slip
them a little galactose and you can
shorten their lifespan cause oxidative
stress inflammation brain degeneration
uh just with like the equivalent of you
know one to two glasses of milk worth of
galactose a day we're not rats though
but given the high amount of galactose
and milk recommendations to increase
milk intake for for prevention of
fractures could be a conceivable
contradiction so they decided to put it
to the test looking at milk intake and
mortality as well as fracture risk to
test their Theory a 100,000 men and
women follow for up to 20 years what did
they find milk drinking women had the
high had higher rates of death more
heart disease significally more cancer
for each glass of milk three glasses a
day was associated with nearly twice the
risk of death and they had significantly
more bone and hip fractures too men in a
separate study also had a higher rate of
death with higher milk consumption but
at least they didn't have higher
fracture rates so a dose dependent
higher rate of both mortality and
fracture in women and a higher rate of
mortality in men with milk intake but
the opposite for other dairy products
like soured milk and yogurt which would
go along with the galactose Theory since
bacteria can for me away some of the
lactose to prove it though we need a
randomized control trial to examine the
effect of milk intake on mortality and
fractures as the accompanying editorial
pointed out uh we better figure this out
soon as milk consumption is on the rise
around the
world darn right we better figure this
out thankfully we do have some new data
um which uh um we can look at uh
obviously you can imagine how that uh
freaked out the scientific community and
so um they pulled out the big guns and
so let me pull that PDF up for
you all right um with the then largest
ever study on milk intake and mortality
showing such adverse effects Harvard
researchers stepped in with
their um uh three famous cohorts the uh
um to form a study twice as big to see
if the Swedish findings were a fluke
following more than 200,000 men and
women for up to three decades and in
they confirmed the bad
news those who consumed more Dairy lived
significantly shorter lives every half
serving
more of regular milk a day was
associated with a 9% increased risk of
dying from cardiovascular causes 11%
increased risk of dying from cancer and
an 11% increased risk of dying from all
causes put
together okay um but wait a
second um we have uh in influential
uh
uh influential organizations advocacy
organizations such as the US national
ostop brosis foundation and the Europe
based International osteoporosis
Foundation which continue to push Dairy
drugs and calcium supplements well
perhaps it's because their objectivity
is compromised by the influence of their
commercial sponsors which include
companies that market you guessed it
Dairy drugs and so
okay so what foods out there may help
our bones well let's turn to that
next even just a single extra serving of
fruits and vegetables per day is
associated with lower bone fracture risk
why well osteoporotic fracture risk is
associated with higher levels of
inflammation in your blood for example C
reactive protein and specifically a more
pro-inflammatory diet those eating
higher on the dietary inflammatory index
have about 30% greater risk of Foster
brosis and Fracture than those eating
more anti-inflammatory diets and a
higher intake of fruits and vegetables
decreases inflammation so that's one
possible reason free radicals may also
play a role in eating away at your bone
suggesting that prooxidant stress May
contribute to osteoporosis both the
total antioxidant power and capacity
people's bloodstreams and diets are
significantly lower than those with
osteoporosis and how do we squash free
radicals and improve antioxidant status
with fruits and vegetables for example
consumption of vitamin C rich foods is
associated with lower risk of hip
fracture osteoporosis and bone loss
every additional increase of 50
milligrams of dietary vitamin C a day
which is about the equivalent of one
orange May lower the risk of hip
fracture by
5% the Third Way fruits and vegetables
may help our bones are through acidbase
balance as we grow older there's a
slight drop in the pH of our blood as
our blood becomes more acidic with age
this is thought to be due to the waning
ability of our kidneys to excrete excess
acid inv vitra studies suggest a drop in
PH may lead to activation of the cells
that break down bone and an inhibition
of cells that build bone back up so how
about eating alkalin forming Foods the
most acid forming foods are meat and
cheese especially fish and the most
alkaline or base forming foods are
fruits and vegetables this may help
explain why if you experimentally remove
fruits and vegetables from people's
diets a mark of bone formation
significantly drops and a mark of bone
loss shoots up and vice versa when you
add fruits and vegetables back into
their daily diets the greater the
estimated ratio between acid forming
foods and alkaline forming Foods the
greater the risk of hip fracture
supporting the rationality less acidic
diets but this was based on
observational data to prove cause and
effect 2-year double blind randomized
control trials were performed in which
the three added servings of fruits and
vegetables are the equivalent of six
extra servings failed to have an effect
but randomized people do the equivalence
of nine daily servings of fruits and
vegetables worth of an alkalin forming
compound and you do see a significant
increase in bone volume and density in
the spine hip and throughout the whole
body are there any fruits and vegetables
that are particularly good that's the
question I'll
address
next
okay so observational studies suggest
that fruit and vegetable consumption may
help protect our bones and an
Interventional trial of an alkaline load
equivalent to nine daily servings
improved bone volume and density have
any specific fruits and vegetabl been
tested yes check it
out
feeding rats dozens of different foods
the fruit found to preserve their bones
the best was the prune and the leading
vegetable was the onion I've talked
already about prunes what about onions
the country with apparently the highest
per capita consumption of onions in the
world is turkey which also has one of
the lowest rates of osteoporotic bone
fractures turkey may have four times
greater daily per capita onion intake
than the United States and four times
lower hip fracture probability
is that just a coincidence though the
problem with trying to correlate country
bycount comparisons is that you don't
know if the people within those
countries who are actually eating those
onions are the ones who are actually
avoiding fractures but in 2017 a
prospective study was published in which
the fruit and vegetable intake of about
1500 older women was followed for nearly
15 years and of all the classes of
vegetables the intake of alium family
veggies such as onions leaks and garlics
were the ones most associated with lower
risk of bone fractures BAS based on a
study of non-hispanic white women 50
years and older those who ate onions on
a daily basis had an overall bone
density 5% greater than those who rarely
ate them um this may not sound like a
lot but could potentially translate into
reducing the risk of hip fracture by
more than
20% why onions maybe it's the quatin
onions are one of the most concentrated
sources of this phytonutrient which can
stimulate the activity of our bone
building cells at least in Petri dish is
also a potent inhibitor of the formation
of new bone eating
cells or could it be the fructan fiber
prebiotics in onions experimentally
infused into the rectum the short chain
fatty acids created by our fiber eating
gut FL have been shown to stimulate
calcium absorption so much so that
adolescence randomized the type of fiber
found in onions about an onion a day
worth for a year significantly increase
their bone mineral density over the
placebo
group in the rodent bone preservation
study a number of spices beat out prunes
and onions with a top dog being another
aliam garlic and in the prospective
human study cruciferous vegetables like
broccoli came in at a close second to
the alium family although there are some
petri dish data supporting the potential
bone benefits of the sulfurane and
cruciferous veggies inhibiting the
formation of bone eaing cells and
appears to protect bone health and mice
the reason I'm singling out onions is
that it's one of only two vegetables
that have actually been put to the test
and clinical trials but how are you
going to come up with a placebo onion
for the control group that's why a group
of innovative Chinese researchers gave
people onion juice versus a fake onion
juice I don't know which sounds worse
but anything for Science and those
randomized to the real onion group
experienced an improvement in a marker
of bone loss over the placebo but the
study didn't last long enough to see if
this translated into tangible bone
benefits but a clinical trial on the the
other vegetable put to the test did the
tomato story starts out like the onion
story there's epidemiological support in
the Framingham osteoporosis study higher
intakes of lycopene the red pigmented
Tomatoes were associated with protection
against bone loss and older men and
women over a period of four years as
well as protection against hip fractures
over 17 years perhaps this helps explain
why studies show that an increased
adherence to a more Mediterranean style
diet is associated with about 20% fewer
hip fractures then there's laboratory
evidence lopine inhibits bone loss in a
Petri dish and preserves bone mass in
rats however so does green tomato
extract which is richer in compounds
such as tomatine rather than lycopene so
maybe there are multiple protective
factors in tomatoes anyway let's feed
people some tomato products and see what
happens postmenopausal women randomized
a lopine in the form of a cup and a
third of regular tomato juice a day
experienced a significant reduction in a
marker of bone loss by month two and the
opposite was found after just a month of
restricting lyrene consumption so no
tomatoes watermelon or other red fruits
like pink grapefruit this suggests that
just regular dietary intakes are
protective but does this translate into
retaining significantly more bone over
time postmenopausal women given about
2third of a cup of tomato sauce a day
for three months suffered significantly
less bone loss than those in ag Mash
group who didn't though it does not
appear that the study subjects were
assigned randomly which could bias the
results so should we go out of our way
to include these specific fruits and
vegetables in our diet normally we're
just left with a can't hurt shrug but a
group of New Zealand researchers put
together a randomized control trial to
find out they developed the Scarboro
fair diet named for the presence of
presumptive bone protecting herbs
Parsley Sage Rosemary and timey from the
song popularized by Simon and Garfunkle
the diet included prunes onions and
tomatoes they compared that to a diet
similarly packed with nine or more
servings of fruits and vegetables but
ones that were not suspected as having
particularly skeleton saving properties
markers of bone turnover were measured
after 3 months and the specially
concocted diet of bone preserving
produce did no significantly better than
the diet packed with nonbone preserving
produce or a diet with just six servings
of fruits and veggies a day suggesting
that the focus should just be on
stuffing your face with fruits and
vegetables of any
stripe
okay so rather than picking or choosing
specific bone boosting produce the
bottom line based predominantly on that
acid base study is to just probably eat
more fruits and vegetables in general um
next we will turn to exercise what's the
best type and frequency of physical
activity for bone health but we're right
about at the hour so why don't we take a
fem minute break um and then we'll come
back and we will talk talk about
physical activity to protect our
skeleton okay what is the best type and
frequency of physical activity for bone
health let's find out right
now
when it comes to bone health it's use it
or lose it physical activity is
considered a widely accessible lowcost
and highly modifiable contributor to
bone health exercise transmits forces
through the skels and generating signals
that are detected by our bone building
cells this is why the national
osteoporosis Foundation International
osteoporosis foundation and other
agencies recommend weightbearing
exercise for the prevention of
osteoporosis these include high impact
exercise such as jumping aerobics and
running as well as lower impact
exercises like walking and weight
training to create those mechanical
signals that spark bone growth but
sufficient intensity and frequency are
critical the large variation in bone
benefit across different studies from
negligible changes to substantial
improvements in bone mineral density
have been attributed to the adequacy of
the exercise regime to improve measures
of bone strength at the spine and hip
the most effective exercise training
protocol appears to be a combination of
progressive resistance and impact
training at moderate to high intensity
low intensity exercise does not appear
to be sufficient for example while
regular walking is often prescribed to
prevent osteoporosis it appears to offer
limited benefit for bone loss prevention
on its own walking has no significant
effect on bone Minal density of the
spine wrist or overall skeleton but it
has been shown to significantly improve
hip bone density in studies that have
lasted more than 6 months more effective
would be brisk walking walking with a
weighted vest or combining walking with
more vigorous exercises such as jogging
stepping or stair climbing non-impact
activities such as cycling or swimming
have been shown to have little or no
effect an elegant study to determine the
optimum frequency of high impact
exercises for bone health involved
hopping on one randomly chosen foot with
a person's other leg acting as the
control women were randomized to hop 50
times on that one same leg either 7 days
a week 4 days a week 2 days a week or
not at all for six months and the brief
daily hopping increased hip bone density
but less frequent hopping was not
effective the only group that built
significantly more bone in their hip on
the jumping versus non- jumping side
within those six months was the 7 day a
week group if you jump 50 times with
about a 10 lb weighted vest on however
you may be able to preserve your hipbone
density with just three sessions a week
instead of every day note weightbearing
impact exercises may be contraindicated
meaning not advisable in those with
severe osteoporosis or recent history of
fractur so make sure you check with your
medical professional before you get
going I love that hopping study so much
brilliant brilliant all right the
greatest
benefit of exercise this is interesting
this was new for me and this is what uh
um really I Center my chapter on
protecting your skeleton in my how not
to age book which will be out in
December all proceeds I received go to
charity um uh uh was the fact that um
you know I'm always thinking of exercise
as increasing bone mineral density
that's how we're going to prevent
fractures but um the greatest benefit of
exercise may have nothing to do with
bone mineral density um as I explained
in the video I will close out with
before we start taking questions uh and
the video is entitled the single most
important thing to do to prevent
osteoporosis bone fractures are you
ready let's do
it
bone mineral density screening may be a
billion doll industry but only 15% of
low trauma fractures are due to
osteoporosis in older women meaning from
a fall no more than from standing height
only 15% of fractures are due to having
low bone density between the ages of 16
80 hip fracture risk increases 13 fold
in men and women whereas the age related
decline in bone mineral density
accounted for only a two-fold increased
risk so the contribution of declining
bone density it to the exponential
increase in hip fracture risk with age
is relatively small the vast majority of
our age related rise and hip fracture
risk appears to have nothing to do with
the measured density of our bones so
what's the main contributor fall risk
without a fall even fragile Hips Don't
fracture Falls are the primary cause of
fractures including vertebral fractures
the disparity between men and women in
hip fracture rates is primarily not
because men have stronger B but because
women fall more often doctors just
asking the simple question do you have
impaired balance can predict about 40%
of all hip fractures more than a bone
scan diagnosis of osteoporosis even a
weak osteoporotic bone is strong enough
to survive normal life activities
without the excessive loading that comes
from a fall impact or in the case of the
spine bending with your back to lift
something rather than your knees the
privacy of Falls in fracture risk
explains a number number of apparent
osteoporosis paradoxes for example
despite the fact that about 75% of your
bone mass may be determined by your
genes the heritability of bone fractures
appears negligible at older ages because
the propensity to fall is much less
inherited it also explains the poor
predictive value of bone density
screening for fractures adding bone
mineral density measures to a hip
fracture risk score based just on age
sex height weight the use of a walking
Aid and cigarette smoke
did little to improve its predictive
power a provocative editorial published
in the Journal of internal medicine
entitled osteoporosis the emperor has no
closeth suggested that it would be safer
and more effective to focus on fall
prevention rather than pharmaceutical
intervention even though only about 5%
of Falls result in the fracture Falls
are very common among the Aged due in
part to age related muscle weakness and
loss of balance where than a third of
those age 65 and older fall each year
and after a hip fracture fewer than 50%
regain their prefracture function in
terms of walking ability and
Independence what can we do to prevent
injurious Falls based on dozens of
randomized control trials the single
intervention most strongly associated
with a reduction in Fall rates exercise
so exercise doesn't just boost bone
density more importantly it also reduces
the number of fall Falls over time by
23% and the number of followers by 15%
so if you followed a thousand people
around age 75 for a year and 480 fell a
total of 850 times without exercise
adding exercise will be expected to
result in 72 fewer fallers and 195 fewer
Falls Tai Chi appears to reduce Falls by
19% balance and functional exercises
like sit to stand may reduce Falls by
24% and multiple exercises typically
balance and functional exercise plus
strength training May reduce Falls by
34% the reduced Falls rate then
translates into fewer fractures a recent
meta analysis found the exercise
interventions mostly using a combination
of resistance exercise to improve lower
limb muscle strength and balance
training cut fracture rates nearly in
half one yearlong trial that combin
strength training with step and jumping
aerobics and focused on balance and
Agility resulted in 74% f were fractures
over the 5year period after the study
ended furthermore More than 70% of the
women in the combo exercise group went
those 5 years without a single injurious
fall compared to less than half of those
in the control group trials on hip
protectors which cushion us sideways
fall on the hip with plastic Shields or
foam pads sewn into special underwear
are often plagued with poor compliance
Studies have not found them to be useful
for reducing hip fracture rat among
those living at home but but trials in
nursing homes or Residential Care
Facilities do show a small reduction
risk translating into about 11 fewer
people out of a thousand suffering hip
fractures due to wearing hip protection
there are also Common Sense measures one
can employ quality improvement trials
involving interventions like patient
education have shown a 10% reduction in
Fall rates for example keep things
within reach so you don't need to use
step stools use non-slip mats in the
bath and shower add grab bars in the
bathroom keep floors clutter-free uh
remove small throw rugs or use
double-sided tape to keep them from
slipping and make sure all staircases
have handrails and adequate lighting you
could also avoid taking walks during
inclement weather and for those who walk
leashed dogs consider choosing smaller
breeds or or ensuring proper training to
prevent them from lunging otherwise the
main ways to prevent fractures may not
have changed much over the decades since
the classic paper entitled strategies
for prevention of osteoporosis and hip
fracture the main ways to prevent these
fractures are to stop smoking be active
and eat
well okay so we have a bone mineral
density focused
mindset right um in medicine for
osteoporosis because there are billions
of dollars invested in scan and drugging
people to track and improve their bone
density but only a small percentage of
hip fracture risk has anything to do
with bone mineral density uh appear is
the best estimate 15% right so it's like
so it's just like most of the risk for
lifestyle diseases like atherosclerotic
heart disease or high blood pressure
has has to do with diet and lifestyle
the money is in theug drugs and
procedures right so that's where our
Focus has been heart disease is all
about you know putting people on statins
and stance right but if we think of wait
a second where is it what about treating
the Cause right um and so if we really
just cared about people not breaking
bones we would be focusing on Falls and
we have this miracle intervention called
exercise resistance exercise to improve
lower limb muscle strength R training
combined with balance training cutting
fracture risk in a half beating out
drugs so it's not just yeah you know you
know safer and cheaper but works better
and of course only has positive side
effects so I like ending on that happy
note of course we're not ending we're
just getting started for the Q&A um so
what we're going to do um we're going to
give nutritionfacts.org staff
five minutes to compile some of the most
commonly asked questions and then I'll
be right back to attempt to answer those
questions I know there was a huge amount
of information thrown at you um tons of
videos that whizzed by and so I don't
want you to think oh wait a second maybe
he addressed that he kind of addressed
that maybe I shouldn't ask a question no
ask the question that's exactly the kind
of question I want because I want to
clarify stuff emphasize stuff so don't
be afraid that
did he answer that already maybe came in
halfway through whatever just ask your
question um we'll compile those
questions we are gonna have lots of time
for questions we set it up that way um
and uh so hopefully I'll be able to help
out with them all right five minutes and
I will be
[Music]
all right all right we are
back okay close down that let me pull up
my list of questions
here okay U feel free to continue to
churn through we have lots of time for
questions so um if you have questions
and questions about answers to my
questions continue to add them and we'll
continue to update this
document okay where did they go hold
on okay here we go nice long list here
okay um I've been told that calcium in
plant milks sold in stores is uh uh is
the same as that found in Tums is that
true should we be avoiding plant-based
milks what about calci banan to food
like calcium fortified orange juice does
that let raise heart attack risk um
though um if you remember back from the
calcium video the reason that uh
supplement calcium seems to increase
cardiovasc disease risk but Food level
calcium does not
is because of that exaggerated Spike
right when you take a th milligrams of
uh you know um you get this huge spike
in calcium in your blood and that makes
your blood more clotty whereas foods
have a little bit of calcium kind of
throughout the day um and so you don't
get that big you don't get all your
calcium all at once and so that would be
the same with uh you know adding some uh
I forget what the uh a number of
milligrams but um in in in like a cup of
soy milk or something but it's way below
what you would get in a supplement um
and so same thing with calcium fortified
orange juice um these are typically in
kind of milk you know standardized kind
of milk doses um and so you would
potentially get the benefits of the
calcium um without the downsides of the
milk sugar galactose or whatever it is
in milk that seems to be increasing
fracture risk um now is that my
preferred Source no what's preferred
Source dark green leafy vegetables low
oxalate green leafy vegetables which
means all greens with the exception of
beak greens Swiss chard and spinach
which are fantastic greens but it just
stings you with their calcium um so but
all other greens like halil and collards
um boxid Etc um that's the best way why
because it's the most nutrient done food
on the planet um and uh and so for all
sorts of reasons has vegetable nitrates
and all sorts of wonderful things you
want um for other parts of your health
but specifically for bone if you
remember that acid base graph the single
most alkaline producing food is the
vegetables those dark green leafy
vegetables um and so um Soh so eating
greens you would get that um that
benefit more than um than kind of you
know fortified food supplements so um
one of the reasons why dark green leaf
of vegetables is one of my on my list my
daily dozen checklist
of the healthiest of healthy foods I
encourage people to eat every day um and
it's available on a free app on iPhone
Android called Dr Gregor's daily dozen
and you can just kind of track your
progress Etc
okay um okay uh next question is my um
is about alal which is a type of um uh a
calcium supplement from an algae what
about that versus some mineral-based
supplements
um calcium is calcium it's an element um
we would not expect any difference if
they at the same dose of the source of
that calcium um so it's not whether it's
you know calcium carbonate or or one of
these other kind of calciums or the
source of the calcium it's the fact you
get so much calcium in your blood so
quickly um and so I would um encourage
people to stay away from calcium
supplements of all Stripes regardless of
what their marketing promotional
materials may tell you
uh next question how important is
adequate hydration and sleep for Osteo
blast our bone building cells you know I
did not run across anything about
hydration or sleep um um with uh bone
Minal density or um fracture risk I
would assume I mean so remember since
most the fracture risk has to do with
Falls right even a fragile bone doesn't
break unless you traumatize it um I you
know I assume if you're sleep deprived I
mean really you you be more wobbly on
your feet and that could increase Fall's
risk but I don't know if it's ever been
studied so it's not something to run
across okay can so that doesn't mean
that there aren't important
relationships but not important enough
to pop up in my searches of uh of
Lifestyle interventions for improving
bone health can I speak to the efficacy
of full body vibration therapy for bone
health Ah that's funny yeah there's
those funny you know things that you
stand on and vibrate uh let us I'm gonna
do a
quick
um let us do a uh I'm going to do a
quick um Pub Med search is National
Library of Medicine largest medical D
database in the world looking for
vibration in the title and fractures and
a metaanalysis and boom there it is
systematic review and meta analysis
let's see what it says at least in the
abstract um whole body vibration ah
interesting okay so it has no effect on
bone Minal Den or microarchitecture
meaning the architecture of your bones
but it does appear to reduce Falls risk
and of course that is an important part
so you could imagine actually reducing
fracture risk if indeed it's true that
reduced uh Falls rate that's really
exciting um but there's only one study
that actually looked at hard fracture
end points um and did not find a
significant um the reduction in the the
the reduction in fracture did not reach
statistical sign significance um and so
uh um we cannot tell for sure if it's
useful but anything it reduces Falls
presumably would be helpful uh next
question do you think working out oh on
a rebounder does any good for bones I'm
assuming I'm assuming a rebounder is
like one of those little mini trampoline
thingies all right let's look it
up okay
trampoline oh that's funny H what comes
up of course when you type in trampoline
fractures is all it's all the horrible
kids breaking their bones jumping on
trampolines okay that's not what we want
let's look for Minal
density okay there we go um
effectiveness of mini trampoline
training on uh balance Mobility gate
strength the bone metal density Etc
older women
osteopenia 12we intervention oh
interesting okay oh same thing no effect
on Bal density so I guess jumping on a
trampoline doesn't have the same impact
you would get like jogging um or you
know vigorously walking but improved
balance wait that would make sense right
improved balance um and uh and
functional mobility okay so hey again
anything improving balance um would be
expected to reduce fracture risk even if
we don't have that endpoint data in
that's exciting all right see I'm
learning I'm learning stuff just along
with you
okay um I've madec ision not to take
drugs for osteoporosis should I bother
with continued dexas scans every two
years um are they inaccurate for small
bone thinned women how accurate our DEA
scans um well they're accurate for what
they're testing for which is bone mural
density but they're not ACC I mean but
in terms of their kind of uh but in
terms of their predictive power they're
very small predictive power um as I
talked about in that last video in terms
of what we really care about which is
whether your bones are going to fracture
or not um so uh but it I mean they
should be just as accurate for I mean
small bone thin women uh have worse tend
to have worse bone mle density just
because they don't have the
weightbearing exercise of carrying
around lots of fat right I mean you
imagine someone who's obese they can
have strong bones because they have like
a 100 pound backpack all over the it's
actually a front pack but they you know
just walking across the room is is is uh
you know is is some exercise whereas
your thin light women um they uh maybe
at higher risk um just because they're
not putting as much weight on their bone
so it's even more important for them to
do weightbearing exercise again that's
for the small amount of fracture wrist
that's for bone Minal density the the
most important thing about exercise is
lower limb training balance training to
prevent Falls
um uh oh in terms of whether you should
continue to get monitored um the use of
of diagnostic testing for lifestyle
diseases is um really comes down to
motivation so it's like uh you know the
recommendation from the uspf is to not
get calcium heart scans um because you
know exposed to to radiation and and and
uh so they basically come out we we're
not sure the pros out with the cons but
if getting a calcium scan if you're the
kind of personality where you are not
going to eat healthy but if I gave you a
a a heart Skin showing you at all this
calcified plaque in your arteries and
that would actually change your life and
you'd actually you know start eating
healthier clean out your cupboards well
then that test could very well save your
life right but if you're the kind of
personality who's like I don't care if
the test is bad or good I'm gonna keep
eating my crappy diet well then why are
you getting the test we only get tests
if we as as physicians in general if we
think it's actually going to affect our
management it's actually going to affect
anything um and so um you know if you
have been like you know lounging on the
couch and you know you know you should
exercise but you're like whatever you
know there's a great new show on Netflix
um but you got a DEX scan showing that
you know compared to two years ago your
bones are even worse now um even farther
off the bell curve if that would would
motivate you to be like okay that's it
I'm going to get into a habit every
single day remember that study it was
really that constant like seven days a
week or maybe only three days if they
did with a weighted vest but it's like
you know lots of high frequency exercise
if that's GNA motivate you then yes I
would say get that
scan um but if it didn't motivate you in
the past and you think it's not gonna
motivate you in the
future um if it's not actually G to
affect anything then uh you know you
could ask yourself why you're getting it
again something to talk to your doctor
about um but that's kind of how I go
into it okay um what's the what's the
best test measure if you're actively
losing bone um is there any type of bone
density screening that doesn't subject
the person to radiation yes there so
there's
ultrasound um but it has not been let me
see what the usbf has to say about uh uh
hold
on let me see what they
say
um okay here we go uh Q us use fter
sound to evaluate peripheral bone sites
um the advantage no exposure to
radiation we knew that um oh and it may
increase access because it's like a
portable device um and so maybe we'd be
able to to to to get out there more
often but oh cannot be routinely used to
initiate or initiate treatment without
dexa just because the treatment studies
um we don't have treatment studies that
have actually followed the ultrasound um
probably because we have a big industry
that invested in the dexa scanning and
studies about dexa scanning um and so
uh okay all
right uh so but yeah both most treatment
guidelines recommend using um the uh
using the Dex
scanning okay um is uh what about
hormone replacement therapy or hormonal
menopausal hormone therapy uh for
improving bone um bone density um well
you can imagine in my preserving your
hormones chapter in uh in how not to age
uh I talk a lot about the pros and cons
of uh hormone uh hormone therapy for
menopause um and uh and that's one of
two things that estrogen systemic
estrogen um is effective at so number
one reducing hot fast hot flash
frequency and severity by about 80%
compared to
Placebo um and so that's it so that's a
consideration if you have intolerable um
so-call vasomotor symptoms like hot
flashes that cannot be um managed
through other means um and I have lots
of videos and all sorts of natural means
to do it um then that's uh at one point
one might consider uh systemic estrogen
use and hormone therapy can also reduce
the risk of osteop IC fracture so for
women with an intact uterus um this is
how the numbers play out I just actually
pulled up some reading basically reading
from the chapter in in uh in in the new
book so this here's a little sneak peek
of how not to age okay so though um so
if uh women with an attacked uterus if
200 women took hormones for 10 years 200
women 10 years we would expect nine
fewer fractures 200 women for 10 years
nine fewer fractures than they would
have if they weren't
on the hormones okay those that's the
upside symptom release like the hot
flashes and F fractures in that same
scenario let's weigh those benefits
those benefits would have to be weighed
against this best best available
evidence for additional heart attacks
fatal or not um two extra
Strokes four more cases of dementia two
more cases of breast cancer one more
case of fatal lung cancer four extra
cases of gobbl ey disease and 10 extra
blood clots though not a single
Partridge or pear tree that's actually I
that's actually written down there I all
right there's a lot of bad humor in in
the book just because I try to keep
things light because it's heavy topic
okay um and so basically I I talk about
how unless the mental pausal symptoms
are absolutely debilitating nothing else
helps it's hard to imagine anyone
accepting that kind of risk benefit um
uh balance based on the um uh uh based
on based on those facts so just a so
nine fewer fractures but four heart Texs
Two Strokes four dementia two more
breast cancer fatal lung cancer
gallbladder disease extra blood Cuts
okay now the safety profile is
better um
for um women who lack a
uterus why because then we can use
estrogen only preparations the reason
that we have to take PR progesterone
along with the estrogen is to protect
against endometrial cancer uh uterine
cancer um which is caused by kind of
unopposed estrogen ah but what if you
were quote unquote lucky enough to have
a
hysterectomy okay so what if you have no
uterus then you can get away you can you
can only use estrogen estrogen only
preparations okay um and so uh so then
um if you just give estrogen you get the
same symptomatic relief in terms of hot
flashes so it wasn't really a
progesterone it was a was the estrogen
that was helping get 11 fewer fractures
so a few more fractures prevented in 200
women over a decade and no extra heart
attacks or dementia and two fewer cases
of breast cancer that's exciting against
six extra cases of gallbladder disease
only one extra blood clot and so the
same two extra
Strokes all right um in either case the
US furer Administration recommends
estrogen only prescribed lowest dose
short duration so it's actually not
clear that lower doses are actually
safer or not okay so that's the uh
that's the bottom line on that you can
run those numbers for yourself and make
up your own mind because that's what
it's all
about okay what do I think of the com
study Co MB study which is evidently D3
K2 strontium magnesium DHA and calcium
if this works does that alter my view of
taking vitamin K EST strontium valuable
supplement for osteoporosis is comb
study never heard of the comb study
let's find out what the comb study is
um
okay home study oh standing for
combination of micronutrients for bone
com study uh interesting published in
some environmental Public Health Journal
um a dozen years ago I've never heard of
it uh okay 12 months consecutive
supplementation
oh come on oh so this is not a
controlled study ah okay so there was no
control in the study so this just kind
of before and
after um and they say it improved uh in
boneal density but that doesn't doesn't
mean that had anything to do with
micronutrient regimen
because um because there was no control
to show I mean maybe everyone's momental
density got better um so what I would do
is actually do a um uh called Web of
science search to see how many Studies
have cited this study so maybe there's
an update maybe this Inspire I mean not
saying I mean there's a value to this
kind of study not in actually telling
you what to do but in spurring research
that could actually tell you what to do
actually spurring research that could
prove cause and effect and so maybe this
study actually made uh maybe they
actually did a a dou blend people
controlled um study
um I am uh I'm skeptical because I
presume I would have run across it but
so you can do a Google Scholar search
you go to Google Scholar it's free you
type in that study um and you see all
the studies ICI didn't and run through
there and see if there's an update if
there was I'd be happy to do a video
about it um either way um in terms of
scrum um I'm just pulling up a Cochran
review which is kind of like or at least
used to be kind of the gold standard for
evidence-based medicine what about
taking
strontium
um
uh uh oh um I looks like I have it
there's it's been updated it looks like
the last one was in oh here we go 2006
let's see what we
got um four
trials um increase in
diarrhea
okay
um but it does say there was an increase
in bone mineral
density um with strontium
supplementation Ah that's
interesting um okay so of course what we
want to know is the important thing is
does this actually reduce fracture risk
um for that I they does not look like
it's said here but again this is 2006
and I'm surprised if that's the latest
Cochran review presumably nothing much
has happened since then but again it's
something that uh I could certainly look
into next time I up update my ostosis
video so thank you so much for that
question okay next uh question I do taii
yoga play pickle ball pickle ball I
always want to try pickle ball one of
these days I'll speak somewhere with a
pickle ball CT and get to play pickle
ball and go to the gym oh go to the gym
twice a week great have osteoporosis
what else can I do oh so they want to
start reclast infusion is there a better
approach okay well hopefully you saw
kind of the pros and cons of uh of those
uh of uh of that uh um class of drugs
and you you can make up your own mind um
and so anything else you can do so I
think the taichi so remember that last
study where talked about the significant
reduction fractions and those randomize
to the uh kind of lower limb uh fact
actually actually pull up that study but
actually talked about taii I think
taichi had 30% lower fractures and then
the lower limb strength trending
combined with balance had 50% so that
was the best but I think taichi was like
30% reduced so that's fantastic but I
would move
to um I I don't know what's involved
with playing pickle ball but um uh I
would move to that resistance training
plus balance seems to be the best
combination so I would incorporate that
maybe you can do that in kind of the gym
twice a week thing or even more
often okay what do I think of
toosa I don't know I don't know if
that's
that's a drug or a supplement I've never
heard of it I am sorry um What factors
contribute to oh young men getting this
disease and she would be screening more
young men
interestingly the uspstf which is again
is kind of this authoritative body on
preventive medicine um uh which is
independent actually independent from
the government independent from
everybody but very well respected um uh
very
resistant to kind of political
maneuverings um or or yeah relatively
resistant to poit political Mo
maneuverings and so that's where people
go to and they've actually concluded
there's not enough um evidence to
support even bone scanning for older men
so they recommend women um at age 65 get
bone scanned for osteoporosis but
there's no recommendation for men uh to
do the same because we just don't have
the data isn't in um so uh so so not
even young men they don't even think
older men um but of course that may
change but as of now there's no
recommendation for screening men period
from the uspstf okay any research on
Osteo strong anytime there's a capital
letter you know I'm thinking it's some
branded thing I've never heard about but
for uh but it goes on to explain um
Osteo strong is a type of bone strength
training program that uses low impact
high intensity exercise to increase bone
density and reduce risk of fractures
okay well if it's low impact then it's
probably not going to help your bone
bone strength right I mean the whole
point is your bone is has this pesio
electric quality which is amazing this
creates electrical signals when the bone
is compressed um you can actually do
this you know on on cadaver bones you
squeeze the bone and attach electrodes
and you actually get an electric charge
coming out I mean that's actually the
the the mo the bone model remodeling
signal actually used electricity isn't
that wild so every time when we jogging
or anything every time we impact that
foot we get this jolt of these the the
little electrical signals telling our
bone cells oh my God this person's off
the couch quick we need a stronger
skeleton again that's only 15% of of um
HIIT fracture risk is is the density of
your bones the strength of your bones
most of it is whether you fall or not so
of course that's the important thing and
whether or not Osteo strong um helps
reduce Falls that would be the my key
question for them that's what we want to
know because that's predominant use of
exercise to protect our bones what does
research say about sauna use for
bones sauna use all right let's look it
up didn't run across it but that doesn't
mean
uh that doesn't mean because I certainly
wasn't looking specifically for it
okay we have
uh
uh two there's there's only one study
and uh published that uh in the medical
literature as far as I can find in
history that looked at bone mental
density and sauna this was a uh son a
bath um this was uh young healthy men um
and they and they found out that bone
mineral
density bone mineral
density increased wait a second of the
left leg increas in Lo okay oh okay oh I
see right leg and left
leg Yeah okay there so there was an
increase it does is there a control
group yeah control group Sonic group and
ah okay wow I would not have thought of
that but there's actually so the one
study the best available balance of
evidence this one study of 23 people 23
healthy young men actually found increas
in bone mineral density after just after
how many how how long did I say say 12
sessions it says 12 sessions of SAA bath
at high temperatures 100 degrees C woo
okay wait a second
100 degrees C isn't that
boiling that's quite a Sonic b anyway
okay
um I don't know if I would
uh I would do sonas just for that but if
you enjoy saas maybe it helps maybe it
helps your bones that's interesting I
would not have thought that okay oh uh
uh the same questioner says On a related
question what about pulse
electromagnetic field
therapy
I do that let's let's see pulse
electromagnetic
field okay let's see if there's a
metaanalysis oh let's do it there's a
2022 meta analysis of randomized control
trials and they
[Music]
found um oh okay so no benefit for bone
real density of the
spine um but may increase the bone Minal
density of the
femur huh that's interesting uh I can't
tell just from the uh just from the uh
abstract who funded the study or how
many studies there were but that's
something something to look look into
that's
interesting all right uh any advice for
a breast cancer survivor who must take
an Aromas inhibitor to prevent
recurrence uh um uh which may affect
bone density well anytime you do
anything that puts your bones at risk
like you're a smoker or something
obviously best thing to do is stop
smoking but if if if if there's anything
that puts you at higher risk that's not
reason just kind of throw your hands up
in the ear oh well no it's it's time to
double down it's like if you have a high
family history of a lifestyle disease a
lot of heart disease in family a lot of
breast can oh my god well then you it's
not time to give up it's like you gotta
you some people can get away with eating
some crap but you really got to eat
healthy right you really got to ex say
you really got to not smoke um because
you have this genetic um risk um or in
this case some pharmacological risk um
and so it's like people who take you
know there's these uh you know antis
psychotics increase uh that make people
obese oh my god well they really got to
watch their diet you know it's no it's
no excuse they they just have to work
even harder than everybody else around
them and so that's what i' recommend for
you I'm using some of the advice that I
talked about here in this webinar hour
okay oh is there a relationship among
poor uh finger and toenail Health
thinning hair and osteoporosis if I have
thinning hair and cracking Nails should
they concerned about osteoporosis no
completely different thing actually hair
and nails may be similar in terms of
they're made of kind of a similar
material this kind of corness material
um uh but uh bones are made of
of something else uh collagen with this
in this mineral Matrix completely
different but um but I do have entire
chapters you will not uh be surprised on
Protec your nail on what you can do
about fingernail health toenail Health
talk about toe fungus talk about brittle
nails and a whole hair loss chapter of
course um and so I talk about you know
uh the failure of bi and supplements for
hair loss utter failure and can actually
be bad because you muck up your
laboratory tests including
life-threatening laboratory tests um but
there's uh the but the evidence is uh
more nuanced with Biotin for nail health
and I talk about you know what the
available data is and if you want to try
it what kind of dose um would be safe um
but yeah that one would not expect uh
that to have anything to do with uh bone
health okay can you reverse osteopenia
yes so osteopenia um uh is is is kind of
a kind of on the on the Spectrum towards
more severe forms of osteoporosis um and
so can we um can basically can we
improve the density the strength the
microarchitecture your bones absolutely
how we going to do that we're going to
do that with um a healthy diet and
lifestyle particularly um so you know
the the type ande exercise I talked
about um there was
um obviously lots of videos on
osteoporosis have dozens I was only able
to show a few of them but you can go so
I have there's a video talking about
people randomizing postm metala of women
to uh soy milk or regular milk and so in
the regular milk group they had a
worsening of of their bone minimal
density over time but in the soy milk
group we think because of the
phytoestrogens and soy um they actually
built more bone over time you know you
think as you get older you lose bone but
actually was able to reverse uh the bone
loss um and and and was significantly
different than the milk group so um and
soy foods are great for um really should
be the first line therapy and it's
recommended as such for um handling
these vasomotor symptoms of
menopause um you know the hot flashes
night sweats Etc so lots of other so I
go to nutritionfacts.org typeing ostosis
lots of other videos um and so uh lots
of other like specific foods and things
like mentioned the prune thing really
quick I got lots of I think I got like
three videos on prunes and Bones all
right um how do I speak slash reason
with my doctors who push oral calcium
supplements um how do I speak reason
with my doctors to P medical treats for
osteoporosis without talking about the
negative negative sides of it um well uh
I mean if uh if you feel that you are
being kind of that you are not being
fully
informed if you I mean the role of the
doctor is to remember that in that video
talking about you gotta scare your
patients into graphic descriptions of
right no that's not the role in my in my
opinion that's not the role of medicine
the role of doctors is to give you the
numbers right if you take the drugs this
is the benefits this is the risk and
guess what it's your body your choice
right um and the doctor's salary should
not depend on whether or not they
prescribed it or not right that's that's
that's that's one of the downsides of
these kind of you know kind of the
kickback culture that has historically
been where you know you get some fancy
new drug and every prescription you
write you get like a you know you know
trip to some fancy Island if you write
enough or them is is
ridiculous um so uh but right I mean you
should the doctor should just be about
informing you based on their knowledge
and experience and so if you feel that
you are being kind of pushed in One
Direction um and not given both sides um
then maybe you need a new Doctor Who
will um take that kind of shared
decision making making approach with you
it's just because the doctor thems um
particularly uh believes that this is
the right course for you doesn't
necessarily mean it is the right course
for you
um but they should describe why they
think it is and and kind of make that
convincing argument or not um and it's
very possible that look the doctors's
just ignorant I mean do they just not
know about all this um the the calcium
risk data that's relatively new
certainly wasn't around when I went to
medical school so maybe just haven't
heard of it look I have the luxury of
just combing through thousands of
Articles all day long every day for
years on end I don't have a clinical
practice anymore so you you know they're
busy they're in the clinic they don't
got time to do this um so I read those
studies so you don't have to um and so
you know they may not be familiar like
in that study that looked at resident
Physicians they just weren't aware of
the you know atypical femur fractures
the OST necrosis in the jaw I mean they
were just so if you're not aware of that
and you just get drug industry
propaganda put all your drugs put all
your patients on these drugs to save
their bones well then you could see how
you you pass them along to your patients
um and so you can educate them you share
with them information um which may be
helpful for their other patients or if
you don't want to make that your job you
can find a doctor that treats you and
your autonomy with more
respect okay please uh address the
effect of carbonated beverages and sodas
on bone health oh you know that was a uh
I wonder if I still have that somewhere
that I was uh um debating whether or not
to add that video so it's like I could
have added 10 more videos but then we
would have less Q&A time it was hard to
kind of make that decision but I have a
whole video on beverages um kind of
besides milk I covered the milk thing um
and so uh soda associated with um an
observational sies with higher um
fracture risk and green tea consumption
associated with significantly lower I
think there's actually Interventional
trials with green tea as well so green
tea good um and uh and soda bad
add okay um oh that's the next question
is green tea recommended for bone
building oh I would love to um let me
see let me pull that up really quick
just because um all right let me uh so
that would
be in my preserving your
bones I'm trying to think of the keyword
to uh
uh here we
go should be right after the um the milk
thing because then I'm like what about
other
beverages there it
is okay what about other beverages
literally that's the sense okay I'm
going to read you from how not to age a
met analysis and effects of alcohol on
ostosis found that compared to
abstainers people who sipped one or two
glasses one or two drinks a day had 34%
increased risk of developing
osteoporosis having more than two a day
two drinks bumped that elevat RIS to 63%
which appears to translate into incre
inre hip fracture risk this may be
partially from alcohol's negative effect
on bone health and also from ah fall
risk due to impaired coordination that
makes total sense okay um ah the section
is called T and T totaling now I know
why okay okay one of the ways sugary
soda appears to cause negative effects
on bone is the same oh is the same way
sodium does oh I didn't even talk about
sodium reduction that's important by
increasing calcium loss through the
urine actually does not appear to be the
caffeine and soda since although
drinking three or more cups of coffee a
day is associated with doubling hip
fracture risk habitual tea consumption
is associated with significantly lower
risk um so coffee bad for the bones soda
bad for the bones tea good for the bones
um at least in these observational
studies um uh hope was raised that the
tea link was causing effect when the
randomized trial found an improvement of
bone turnover markers in women and
actually higher bone mass oh and tfed
rats well okay but in the Minnesota
Minnesota Green Tea trial which is the
largest and longest clinical trial in
the effects of green tea extracts on
postmenopause women no significant
benefit on bone mental density was found
ah bummer okay so we do not have cause
and effect evidence that tea is good for
the bones just uh the fact that tea
drinkers tend to have um fewer
fractures oh that's a bummer okay all
right uh well you heard it there first
you think I would know this because I
wrote that but it's a long book um
that's why I I have to go to it okay how
would oh my God okay um uh let's I think
everyone for joining me uh stay safe be
kind eat your
vegetables um and protect those
[Music]
bones
for